hey guys this looks like a fun one
someone sent me this in an email it
gives us two circles in a rectangle and
it wants us to solve for the height X
the base of the rectangle is 18 cm this
circle's diameter is 16 cm and this
circle's diameter is 10 cm if you want
to try on your own pause it right now
because I'm going to solve it in three
two 1 first let's rotate the two
diameters to be horizontal and let's
label the centers of both of the circles
this diameter of 10 is going to split
into two radiuses of 5 cm and this
diameter of 16 will split into two
radiuses of 8 cm and yes radiuses is a
plural of radius you could also say radi
and then from the center of the smaller
Circle let's drop a vertical line and
same thing for the center of the larger
Circle this piece is the same thing as
the radius of the smaller Circle so
it'll be equal to 5 cm and then this
portion right here is equal to the
radius of the larger Circle so it'll be
equal to 8 cm so now since the entire
base is 18 this is five and this is 8
that leaves 5 cm left over for this part
but this cannot be right because the
radius is 8 how is five greater than
eight so this thing is definitely not
drawn to scale if you're curious I
actually drew it in geogebra this is
what it would look like if it was drawn
correctly here's the same two circles
but this would be at a much steeper
angle up on top and then for the one
that is drawn to scale if you drop this
vertical line and this vertical line and
bring the measurements down we have five
five and8 and this makes makes more
sense the five fits within the eight so
this is definitely not to scale this is
what it should look like I looked into
this a little bit more this is something
from it looks like a textbook it doesn't
say what textbook so I can't find the
original Source but this might be the
original source and even in the textbook
the problem is definitely not drawn to
scale the textbook looks a lot more like
this incorrect one than it does the
correct one so I think it's funny even
the textbook is blatantly not to scale
but I think even though it's not to
scale we can still solve this so let's
keep going from the center here let's
draw this horizontal line and it'll be
perpendicular to the vertical line and
same thing from this Center let's draw a
horizontal line this portion of the
height is the same thing as the radius
of the larger Circle so this is going to
be equal to 8 cm and then this portion
of the height is the same thing as the
radius of the smaller Circle so it's
going to be equal to 5 cm so the
distance from here to here is still
unknown let's call it question mark cenm
or even better let's give it a variable
let's call it y CM so now we just got to
solve for y and it'll be pretty easy to
figure out X I see a right angle right
here so if we connect these two we'll
have a right triangle and this
hypotenuse is a distance of the five
radius plus the 8 radius so it'll be 13
cm and let's focus on this triangle the
height of this triangle will be y cm and
the base will be 5 cm and now we can do
Pythagorean theorem it says a^2 + b^2
will equal c^2 or in other words 5^ 2 +
y^2 will equal 132 52 is equal to 25 and
13 s is equal to 169 and we can bring
down everything else next we want to get
this y^2 alone on the left hand side so
let's subtract 25 from both sides on the
left hand side we have y^2 and on the
right hand side 169 minus 25 is 144 next
we can square root both sides of the
equation and that'll give us Y is equal
to 12 this is very important let's put a
box around it we're not going to need
this stuff anymore and let's bring this
up here and now we can rewrite this y CM
as 12 CM let's pull out these two
measurements and go back to our original
diagram our goal was to solve for x
which is the height of this rectangle
well the Height's also equal to 5 + 12 +
8 and then 5 + 12 + 8 is equal to 25
let's give it a label of centimet and
put a box around it this is the answer
to our question X is equal to 25 cm how
exciting